Finding Aid for Phelps Brothers (Manton, Mich.) records, 1890-1964
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Phelps Brothers (Manton, Mich.) records 1890-1964
Phelps Brothers (Manton, Mich.)
1 linear foot
85298 Bb.2/2
Records of the retail business activities of the Phelps family of Manton, Michigan in Wexford County.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of D. Maynard Phelps (donor no. 6970 ) and came to the library in September 1983.
The record group is open to research.
In 1893, Charles D. Phelps formed a partnership with James H. Baker in Manton, Michigan (Wexford County) thus beginning a family business enterprise that continued until 1963. Phelps had attended Michigan Agricultural College and the University of Michigan, but when problems with his vision developed, he was forced to terminate his formal education. He returned to Northern Michigan where he taught school on occasion in addition to working as a mason and builder.
Phelps' business encompassed many kinds of activities: milling, farming, lumbering, cutting and selling ice, purchasing and selling potatoes and grains, as well as the retailing of farm supplies, coal, lumber, and building supplies.
During its history, the firm went through many changes in organization. In 1914, Baker retired, leaving Phelps sole owner of the enterprise. From 1915 to 1920, the firm was known simply as Chas. D. Phelps, and from 1920 to 1927 as Chas. D. Phelps and Sons. With Phelps' death in 1929, two sons (Charles L. and D. Maynard) continued the business as Phelps Bros. It remained this until 1963 when the family sold the firm to Samuel W. Williams.
This record group covers the years 1890 to 1964 and consists of the diaries and a biographical sketch of Charles D. Phelps, a history of the business written by D. Maynard Phelps, and various business records. The business records series consists of income tax returns, papers pertaining to the sale of the business, and miscellaneous inventories, journals and a ledger.
Subjects:
Business records.; Manton (Mich.).; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Wexford County (Mich.).; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.
Contributors:
Phelps, Charles D. (Charles Dellen), 1859-1927.
Genre Terms:
Diaries
- Diaries and history
  - Diaries of Charles Dellen Phelps, 1890-1893 and 1895 (Box 1)
  - History of the business (Box 1)
- Business Records
  - Income Tax Returns, 1919-1962 (1924 lacking) (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers and Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Inventory Books
    - July 1911-July 1923 (Box 1)
    - July 1931-July 1964 (Box 1)
  - Journals
    - March 1896-May 1897 (Box 1)
    - March 1920-December 1926 (Box 1)
    - January 1927-June 1933 (Box 1)
    - July 1933-December 1943 (Box 1)
    - December 1943-March 1949 (Box 1)
    - April 1949-November 1960 (Box 1)
    - December 1960-June 1963 (Box 1)
  - Ledger, 1925-1928 (sampled) (Box 1)